Register of the Jack Belden Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jack Belden Papers
1935-1989
90020
Hoover Institution Archives
4 boxes, 1 oversize box (3.0 linear feet)
Correspondence, news dispatches, and other writings, relating primarily to the Sino-Japanese War, American military operations in North Africa, France, Belgium and Germany, the occupation of Germany, and the publication of China Shakes the World. Includes correspondence with Agnes Smedley.
Belden, Jack, 1910-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
The collection was acquired by the Hoover Instituion Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1910, February 3 Born, Brooklyn, New York
1926 Graduated, Summit High School, New Jersey
1931 Graduated, Colgate University, New York
1931-1933 Seaman - Java, Phillippines, Germany, and South America
1933 Teacher, Peking University, China
Late 1930s Reported on the Second Sino-Japanese War for the United Press International
Early 1940s Covered Italy, North Africa, and Burma for Time and Life magazines
1943 Returned to the United States Author, Retreat with Stilwell
1944 Author, Still Time to Die
1946 Returned to China
1949 Author, China Shakes the World
1989 June 3 Died, Paris, France
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Jack Belden cover his career as an American journalist. He was a foreign correspondent in China during the Second Sino-Japanese War; in China, Burma, North Africa, and Europe during World War II; and in China during the Civil War.
The materials, consisting of correspondence, news dispatches, writings, diary, and notes, relate primarily to the Second Sino-Japanese War, American military operations in North Africa, France, Belgium, and Germany, the occupation of Germany, the publication of China Shakes the World, and reviews of his writings. An insight into United States Army operations in Europe and the Far East during World War II is also provided.
The Jack Belden papers were acquired originally in 1990. Incremental materials, received in 2008, have been added alphabetically at the end of the register by the original series.
Arrangement
Arranged into seven series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Office File, Writings, United States Army File, Incremental Material, and Oversize Material.
Smedley, Agnes, 1892-1950.; China--History--1937-1945.; China--History--Civil War, 1945-1949.; Germany--History--1945-1955.; Journalists.; Military government.; Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1937-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Africa, North.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Western Front.
- Biographical File, 1943, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings, diary, and identification cards, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Clippings about Jack Belden's injury sustained in Oran, Western Algeria, and from Who's Who in the East, 1943, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Diary, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Identification cards issued by British forces, and United States Army Forces in the Middle East, Cairo, Egypt, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Miscellany, 1943, undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Correspondence, 1940-1984, undated
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Unidentified, 1951-1984, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Ackarman, Laura V., 1944 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Amalia, Karl F., 1943 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Australia-China Society, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Baker, Gladys, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Berry, Bertha L., 1943, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Brajbihari, Vijan, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Brents, B. P., 1943 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Campbell, Kathleen, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Canfield, Cass, 1948-1950 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Chapman, H. Owen, undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Colonel Unni Nayar Commemoration Volume Committee, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Copps, Kenneth, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Daily Worker, undated (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Downs, K. T., 1943 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Dudley, Genevieve, undated (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Ediciones Ló Negri, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Finke, Mary Berkeley, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Finnell, Peggie J., 1951 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Fry, Elisabeth D., 1950 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Gadsden, Jeanne?, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Gilman, Labelle, undated (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Gloonan, Marjorie, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Gordey, Michel, 1953 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Gray, Josephine, undated (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Green, Eleanor B., undated (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Groom, Bessie, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Hanneman, Erma, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - Harper & Brothers, 1948 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Hart, John N., 1960, undated (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Hirschtick, A. B., 1943 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Howard, Ruth H., 1944 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - Hughes, Carol, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Kenfield, Lu, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - Kennedy, Kathleen, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Koo, T. T., 1980 (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - Leonhardy, Hans, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - Lifschutz, Anne, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - Lumbert, Hortense, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 43)
  - McAllister Carver, Laura, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 44)
  - McDonald, Thomas H., 1944 (Box-folder 1: 45)
  - Manning, James Leeds, Mrs., 1950, undated (Box-folder 1: 46)
  - Marshall, Ann N., 1944 (Box-folder 1: 47)
  - Meijer, Elizabeth T., undated (Box-folder 1: 48)
  - Morehouse, Harold, Mrs., 1943 (Box-folder 1: 49)
  - Nagler, Rudyard, undated (Box-folder 1: 50)
  - Patrick, Jim, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 51)
  - Raburn, R. W., undated (Box-folder 1: 52)
  - Rajalingam, S. Durai, 1960 (Box-folder 1: 53)
  - The Reporter, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 54)
  - Rood, Andra de, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 55)
  - Ruth, Harry S., 1943 (Box-folder 1: 56)
  - Sanders, Jessie, undated (Box-folder 1: 57)
  - Schumacher, Joachim, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 58)
  - Sharper, Frida, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 59)
  - Shepard, Chas D., 1944 (Box-folder 1: 60)
  - Smedley, Agnes, 1947-1950, undated (Box-folder 1: 61)
  - Smith, Laura, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 62)
  - Snow, Ed, 1962 (Box-folder 1: 63)
  - Sommers, Martin, 1948 (Box-folder 1: 64)
  - Spradling, Ernie, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 65)
  - Stilwell, Theodore R., 1943 (Box-folder 1: 66)
  - Suggett, Allen Holman, 1950 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Thatcher, Blanche M., 1943 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Time (magazine), 1943 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Tischner, Paul, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Traverse, Virginia, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Tully, Betty, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Van Winkle, Howard, 1951 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Vincent, Ruth B., 1944 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Warren, Tully E., 1943 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Washburn, Ruth E., 1943, undated (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Wien, C. K., 1944 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Weiner, Jack, Mrs., 1944 (Box-folder 2: 12)
- Office File, 1936-1945, undated
  Clippings and printed matter, newspaper dispatches, notes, and telegrams relating to Jack Belden's work as a war correspondent, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Clippings and printed matter, 1936-1939 (Box-folder 2: 13-15)
  - Newspaper dispatches, undated (Box-folder 2: 16-20, Box-folder 3: 1-4)
  - Notes, undated (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Telegrams, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Writings, 1939-1949, undated
  Typescript and printed copies of Jack Belden's writings and reviews of his books, arranged chronologically
  - Fragment, undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - "In the Air" and "Japan's Drive on Hankow,", undated (Box-folder 3: 8)
    Typescript
  - Reviews
    - "The New Fourth Army,", circa 1939 (Box-folder 3: 9)
      Includes a printed copy of the article
    - Retreat with Stilwell and China Shakes the World, 1949, undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
      Typescript and printed copy
- United States Army File, 1944-1945, undated
  Citation, instructions, maps, memorandum, press release, report, statement, and statistical data, relating to strategic planning and operations, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Citation for War Department Distinguished Unit--16th U.S. Infantry Regiment and 1st U.S. Infantry Division, undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Instructions to U.S. military government officers relating to the military government in Germany, undated (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Maps, undated (Box-folder 4: 3)
    12th Army group outline maps of France and Japan, including one reflecting the plan of Japanese operations against Hankow and action against Tienchiachen
  - Memorandum and press release, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Record of plan of war, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Report on coalition government, by Mao Tze-Tung (Mao, Zedong), undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Statement by Colonel Myers to Jack Thompson about the organization of the army security force and the headquarters security force (Palace Guard) and the operations in which they were involved, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Statistical data on the German army, undated (Box-folder 4: 8)
- Incremental Material, 1930s-1989, undated
  Biographical details, correspondence, reports, and writings received as increments to the collection, arranged chronologically by the original series
  - Biographical File, 1989
    - Biographical sketch probably written by Beatrice Weber in 1989 and introductory comments by R.K. McCabe, circa 1989 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - Obituaries, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 10)
      Includes a letter to the editor from New York Times, 1989 June, and photocopies of all obituary messages
  - Correspondence, 1988-1989
    - Unidentified, 1989-1990, undated (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - Belden, David, undated (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - Buchman, A. H., 1989 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Christopher, Paul, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - Durdin, Tillman, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - McCabe, Robert, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 4: 16)
    - McManus, Jason, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    - Schaller, Michael, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - Timmerman, Kenneth, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - Weber, Beatrice, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Office File, 1936-1941
    - Reports on China relating to drug trade, criminal activities, political terrorism in Shanghai, and a recollection of pre-war Shanghai by M. C. Ford, correspondent and editor of the Shanghai Evening Post, 1936-1941, undated (Box-folder 4: 21-22)
  - Writings, 1939
    - "The New Fourth Army," pamphlet, 1939 (Box-folder 4: 23)
      Printed copy
- Oversize Material, 1935-1944, undated
  Scrapbooks and writings by Jack Belden, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Scrapbooks, 1935-1938 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
    Two volumes Writings by Jack Belden
    - "Sequel to Salerno,", undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - "Hey, Soldier, I'm Wounded!" Life, 1943 September 27 (Box-folder 5: 4)
      Includes an account and photocopies of photographs of the "Battle of Salerno"
  - Miscellany, 1944, undated (Box-folder 5: 5)
    Photocopies of a photograph of Jack Belden's injured leg, undated, and cover page of Life, 1944 March 20